<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of some objections lately raised against Dr. John Colbatch his hipothesis : together with some observations on his essay of alkaly and acid and it's [sic] appendix. / By Dr. Francis Tuthill of Dorchester.</title>
            <author>Tuthill, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3387</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16857</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077728</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077728</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2278:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of some objections lately raised against Dr. John Colbatch his hipothesis : together with some observations on his essay of alkaly and acid and it's [sic] appendix. / By Dr. Francis Tuthill of Dorchester.</title>
                  <author>Tuthill, Francis.</author>
                  <author>Colbatch, John, Sir, 1670-1729. Doctrine of acids in the cure of diseases farther asserted.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 41 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. and J. Churchill, and for Robert Gaylhard bookseller in Corchester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Marsh's Library, St. Patrick's, Dublin, Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Colbatch, John, --  Sir, 1670-1729.</term>
               <term>Blood --  Analysis.</term>
               <term>Diseases --  Causes and theories of causation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151838:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF SOME OBJECTIONS Lately RAISED Againſt Dr. <hi>JOHN COLBATCH</hi> HIS HIPOTHESIS. Together with Some <hi>Obſervations</hi> on his <hi>ESSAY</hi> of <hi>ALKALY</hi> and <hi>ACID</hi> and it's <hi>APPENDIX.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Dr. <hi>Francis Tuthill</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Via trita, via tuta.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>J. Churchill,</hi> and for <hi>Robert Gaylhard</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151838:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151838:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have read over the Doctrin of Acids, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your Solutions are very Ingenious: I would fain acquieſce in them, that ſo I might give neither my Self, or the World any further Trouble; but I aſſure you I cannot. I am not inſenſible how dangerous a Thing it is to expoſe my Self to the common Cenſure in this ſcribling Age; and I had not appeared in Public again, had not ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Friends, whom I ſhould have diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by a Refuſal, preſt and urg'd me to a freſh Attack. I hope you will meet with nothing of a cavilling Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, nor any Thing that looks like Inſulting in this Treatiſe; I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin you will have any Occaſion to write a Recantation. No doubt but you will find a Defect in ſome of my Arguments, and make your Animadverſions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your uſual Candour. I would not be thought to patronize Alkalies ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151838:3"/>far as to be at Enmity with all Acids. I can entertain a good Opinion of them in many Caſes, and hope to ſee the Uſe of them Eſtabliſh'd in thoſe Caſes upon ſurer Foundations than ever. All that I contend for, is, that Alkalies are not of ſuch a poyſonous Nature as you repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them. They were created to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, in no wiſe to deſtroy, us. I ſhall uſe the ſame Method, in replying to your <hi>Anſwers,</hi> as you have done to my <hi>Objections:</hi> Take 'em in Pieces, and where they ſeem defective make my <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</hi> The firſt of my <hi>Objections</hi> did run thus, If Alkalies are the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Diſtempers, then <hi>poſito Alkali ponitur morbus.</hi> But this will not hold Good; for all healthy Perſon's <hi>Serum</hi> is Alkalizated, as is evident from it's green Colour when mixt with Syrups of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets. May not this Phaenomenon then ariſe rather from a due Mixture of the Principles, then from any violated Habit of Blood? Your <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this is pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty long; but the moſt material Parts of it are theſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt of which is, That tho' there are Alkaline Particles in healthy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Blood, yet not enough to cauſe a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151838:3"/>Diſtemper. They abound much more in Sick Perſons. <hi>Reply,</hi> If you pleaſe to compare the Alkaline Spirit, that you extracted from the conſumptive Blood, with that which the healthy Blood af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded, you will find no great Diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, eſpecially if you conſider the <hi>Caput Mortuum</hi> of the ſound Blood. For you ſay, that it being broken into ſmall Atoms, each Atom appeared to be ſo many little Bodys of Fire in your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſcope. That there is not the leaſt Spark of Fire in the Blood, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to prove anon; wherefore 'tis not irrational to ſuppoſe, that thoſe lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid Atoms were of the Family of Salts: And if Salts, then Alkaline, according to the Rules of your own Hypotheſis. But then (you reply) the tabid Blood would have yielded much more Alkaly, had the great quantity of luxuriant Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaly been thrown upon the Lungs. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks this ſeems a little ſtrange. For, if you remember, the conſumptive Perſon did ſweat prodigiouſly. Now you make Sweat to be nothing but an excrementitious Alkaly. If this Alkaly then was carried off in ſuch quantities,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151838:4"/>it could not well abound ſo much in the Lungs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Part of your <hi>Anſwer</hi> to my firſt <hi>Objection,</hi> that no Man may be ſaid to enjoy perfect Health; that this Alkaly, which is found in the Blood of every Man, is the Principle of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>Reply,</hi> If this be true, then Old Men, who are near a Diſſolution, in whom Nature is almoſt ſpent, muſt needs have their Blood ten-times more deeply tinctured with Alkalies than Young Men. This may be ſo for ought I know. I have experienced nothing to the contrary as yet, having none of your Conveniences at Hand. But I am of Opinion, that if either of us were to diſtil the Blood of a phlegmatic Aged Conſtitution, and that of a bilious Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venile, the latter's Alkalies would not fall ſhort of the formers: My ſecond <hi>Objection</hi> was;</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is another way of diſcovering an Alkaly, beſides that of it's Appearance, and that is by it's Effects, <hi>viz.</hi> it's Fermentation with Spirits of Vitriol. Now I aver this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum will not ſerment with the aforeſaid Spirit. I believe I might be ſomewhat
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151838:4"/>deceiv'd in making this Experiment. For I have found ſince, that the Spirit of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol was not Good, neither did I allow enough in Proportion to the Serum. But this I have Experimented ſince with what Care I could. I took ſuch Serum as would turn Syrups of Violets Green, put into a little Pot, and poured ſome Oyl of Vitriol on it. It immediately became ſomewhat hot, but 'twas far from being intenſely ſo. I took ſome more of the ſame Serum, put it into another Pot, poured Spirit of Sulphur on it. The Spirit gave it a very languid Heat, ſcarcely exceeding luke-warm. After this I took ſome grumous Parts of the ſame Blood, poured ſome Oyl of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol on them. They grew not ſo warm as the Serum did with the Oyl: There were very few Degrees of Heat in them. From all which I infer, that, tho' there may be ſomewhat of an Alkaly in the Blood, which I never deny'd; yet not ſo great a quantity as you imagin, a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Stock for all Diſeaſes: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed upon the Suppoſal of five Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the Blood (which no <hi>Chymiſt</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys) why might not either thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples offend and breed Diſtempers as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151838:5"/>well as the Salts? In <hi>page</hi> 67. you are at a loſs how to interpret my warm Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I mean Alk. Particles, ſuch as I beleive the Blood abounds with in ſome Feavors, in which I grant you, that Acids are of Uſe. But yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not away with your Notion of Feavors. A Feavor (ſay you in <hi>page</hi> 68.) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a Conſtipation of ſome of the Emunctories, ſo that the Excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious Alkaly, which ſhould be carry'd off by them is detained in the Blood, which by breaking it's Globules, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Doctrin does not ſeem to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond at all with your Practice. For, <hi>Spirit. Vitrioli</hi> and other Acids, which are very Stiptic, the Uſe of which you applaud in Feavors, ſhould methinks conſtipate the Emunctories more cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And then they being of a very fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nature, ſhould fetter or retain theſe Excrementitions Alkalies. Again, if Feavors are occaſioned only by a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of theſe Alkalies, then it muſt follow, that whenever they have free Vent, the Feavor muſt abate. But the contrary has been ſometimes experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; where the Patient has ſweated ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry liberally and yet dy'd at laſt. Iſ
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151838:5"/>this will not ſerve the turn, I hope to make it appear anon, that Alkalies are not capable of breaking the Globules, and making ſuch a Buſtle in the Blood: But I cannot but ſpeak one Word or two in their Defence before I go any further. I am very apt to think, that in ſome Feavors, eſpecially Peſtilential and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, the Spirits are primarily affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted according to the Hypotheſis of the Ingenious Dr. <hi>Morton,</hi> witneſs thoſe Symptoms which attend the <hi>Genus nervo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum</hi> immediately upon the firſt Seizure. But you muſt not admit this Notion, the Soyl which you muſt lodge in the Blood, and thence be communicated to the Spirits. Well, let it be ſo; I will not diſpute it: The difficulty on your ſide will be great ſtill. For, tho' I ſhall readily grant the Globules to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the aforeſaid Feavors; yet, 'twill be a hard Matter to convict Alkalies of thoſe Tragical Diſorders. For <hi>firſt,</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhews, that nothing is more proper in thoſe Caſes malignant (I ſhall adventure to uſe the Term, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it has been ſo ſcouted of late) then <hi>Pulv. è chel. rad. Serpentar.</hi> nay, <hi>Sp. C. C.</hi> it ſelf given in a proper Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151838:6"/>But <hi>ſecondly,</hi> nothing does ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily diſſolve the Maſs of Bood, or ſeparate it's Principles as Acids, which I ſhall prove by and by, when I come to ſpeak ſomething of Dropſies. But this long Diſcourſe of the Heat of the Blood, does naturally lead me to conſider ſomewhat of it's Flame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> And here the Life of Man you take to be a Fire or Flame, and all we Eat and Drink, together with the Air we draw in to be Fuel for this Flame. The chief Arguments you bring to confirm this Doctrin, are taken from the Excrements of this Flame and it's Fuel. The Excrements are Alkalies, which are near of kind to Aſhes, the Relicts of other Flames: And for it's <hi>Pabulum,</hi> 'tis Acid and Sulphur the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Pabulum</hi> of all Flames. Here I muſt confeſs you talk very ingeniouſly, and highly improve the Notions of that great Philoſopher. But let us examin this Hypotheſis a little. As for Alkalies, I confeſs they are of the ſame Nature with Aſhes and Soot: Yet it does not follow, that becauſe Alkalies are found in the Blood there muſt be a Flame too. We extract Alkaly out of ſeveral Herbs.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151838:6"/>'Tis true the Herbs muſt be calcined firſt. But certainly the Salt was pre-exiſtent in the Herb before the Calcination, or elſe the Fire produced it <hi>de novo,</hi> which you will by no means admit. The Inference then is plain. I will not adventure to ſay any Thing of Crabs-Claws, Oyſter-Shells, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> leaſt you ſhould make them the Recrements of a vital Flame. Come we next to the <hi>Pabulum</hi> and that is Acid and Sulphur. That Bodies in which Sulphur is predominant, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamable no body queſtions: But that ſuch in which Acid is the chief Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſhould burn, looks like a Paradox. To inſtance in a few: <hi>Acet. Spirit.</hi> of <hi>Vitriol Suc. Limon. &amp;c.</hi> are ſo far from promoting Flame, that they immediately quench it: And indeed I know but one Acid in Nature, which is inflamable, and that is <hi>Nitre.</hi> But then this Vital Flame is not of a Nature with Culinary Flames. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Since the <hi>Pabulum</hi> is the ſame, methinks the Flame ſhould be ſo too. <hi>Again,</hi> tho' you ſpeak ſo much of this Vital Flame, yet you do not (as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) much care to fix the Place of it's Exiſtence. I ſuppoſe it muſt be in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151838:7"/>the Blood, if any where. Now 'tis very hard to ſuppoſe a Flame in that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, of which no Part is inflamable. If you open a Vein and the Blood ſpouts out reeking hot on the Fire, it will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately quench it. So that methinks, theſe Notions ſeem to be a little too finely ſpun. Acid and Sulphur did ſupport human Life, Men live upon Coals, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in which there is ſtore of Acid and Sulphur, that we cannot ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Air is evident: For tho' there is no Fire in the Blood, there is Motion undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Now the Nitro-acreal Particles give a freſh Fermentation (or Motion) to it, and free it from Coagulation. If you are not ſatisfied with this, conſult the Ingenious Dr. <hi>Mayow.</hi> But then the Blood has heat and warmth; and theſe are the Properties of Fire. <hi>Anſw.</hi> May they not be excited by it's Motion? No (you <hi>Reply</hi>) we are much warmer in Bed, when we uſe no Exerciſe, then when we are up and in Motion. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Body indeed is in no Motion there; but the Blood is greater then when we are out of our Beds; and 'tis impoſſible ſhould be otherwiſe. For, do not the Bed-cloaths protect us from the Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151838:7"/>of the ambient Air? And are not a great many of the Volatile Alkalies detained by them, which reflecting upon the Body, warm it, and accelerate the Motion of the Blood. But after all, if we move violently, when out of our Beds, we are much warmer, than when in them. You are pleas'd to <hi>Object,</hi> 'tis impoſſible meer Motion ſhould cauſe any Heat in fluid Bodies. How ſo? Let a Man put <hi>Spirit. Corn Cerv.</hi> and <hi>Spirit. Vitrioli</hi> together and obſerve their Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. They will ſoon grow warm. 'Tis evident, they do not ſtand ſtill, but move very briskly before they are warm. And what is the Heat of theſe Bodies occaſioned by, but their Fermentation or inteſtine Motion? Surely it cannot be by Accenſion. My third <hi>Objection</hi> was this;</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If Alkalies are the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of Diſtempers, whence is it, that in Dropſies, Catarrhs, ſome Gouts and other Diſeaſes, we find the Texture of the Blood ſo thin? 'Tis obſervable, that thoſe Particles you term Alkalies, the more the Blood is ſaturated with them, of the more thick Conſiſtence it is, as we ſee in Pleuriſies, Rheumatiſms and other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151838:8"/>Inflamatory Caſes (in which Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, if in any, the Alkalies abound) is not then it's Tenuity rather to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to Acids? Do not Acids immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately put the Blood in a Fuſion, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it thin? Your <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this is, that 'tis not the Thinneſs of the Blood is the only Cauſe of theſe Diſtempers, but a Deſtruction of the Tone of the Parts. Here methinks you do not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue ſo fairly. For, you mention little or nothing of the Deſtruction of the Tone of the Parts in your Etymologies of Diſtempers till now. And why may I not as well ſay, in Inflamatory Caſes the Blood is not affected with any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaline Particles? Theſe Inflamations on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ariſe from a Deſtruction of the Tone of the Parts: Eſpecially, if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what you aſſerted in your Notion of Feavors: For there the Emuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are very much out of Order. But (you <hi>Object</hi>) ſince Acids will reduce the Blood to it's due Conſiſtence, it is not reaſonable to ſuppoſe they ſhould be the Cauſe of it's Fuſion. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acids will reſtore the Conſiſtence of the Blood I ſhall examin by and by: I fear they will not. But this I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151838:8"/>of, they will put it in a Fuſion. 'Tis well known that your celebrated Oyl of Vitriol taken alone, or tho' in a Vehicle, if in too great Quantity, kills. Now how does it kill? Does it not by diſſolving the Maſs of Blood, by ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the Grumous Parts from the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and breaking it's Texture after the ſame Manner as it does that of Milk? Sure I am, that Blood coagulated by the aforeſaid Oyl, does much more reſemble Whey and Curds than Jelly of Harts-horn. Now then, what is all this but an extraordinary Fuſion? And if a large Doſe will make ſuch mad Work, and put the Blood into ſo great a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; certainly a leſs Doſe muſt cauſe ſomewhat of a Fuſion. And 'tis rational to believe that Oyl of Vitriol is proper only in thoſe Diſtempers, where the Blood is too thick; very pernicious in ſuch as have it too thin. And here I am very glad, that you ſo opportunely give us your Sentiments of <hi>Dropſies.</hi> A Dropſie (ſay you) or the Thinneſs of Blood in that Diſeaſe does not proceed from Acids, but over much Drinking. <hi>Anſw.</hi> That large Draughts (there being little Evacuation by Urin) render the Blood
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151838:9"/>more thin is very obvious. But now the Patient had no ſuch deſire for Drink, till the Diſtemper was actually upon him. So that the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is, what firſt brought on the Diſtemper. Was it not a Weakneſs of Blood or Want of due Conſiſtence. I do not ſee how you can well deny it. But then (you <hi>Reply</hi>) let it be ſo, 'tis Impoſſible, Acids ſhould occaſion this ill Habit of Blood. For, Hydropical People are Thirſty, and 'tis ridiculous to imagin that Acids ſhould excite Thirſt, when they are the only Things in the World that will quench it. <hi>Anſw.</hi> This I confeſs, at firſt Sight, looks like an invincible Argument: But I muſt crave leave to weigh it a little. That Acids drank or held in the Mouth uſually quench Thirſt, is an undeniable Truth. Tho' twill hardly hold Good in all Caſes. For, let a Man drink Brine, which is very much impregnated with Acids, or eat high-ſeaſoned Meats; I believe tho' he were a <hi>Stoick</hi> he would immediately grow Thirſty. But com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Salt is not an Acid of a right Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Well, admit this. The moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Acids that I know for ſuppreſſing Thirſt, are <hi>Oyl. Vitriol. Spirit. Vitriol.</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151838:9"/>Now I hope to make it appear, that theſe or Acids of the ſame Nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in the Blood may provoke Thirſt. I prov'd juſt now, that Oyl of Vitriol had an ugly Faculty of coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating the Blood, or ſeparating it's Serum. That there is a Separation of the Serum in Dropſies is evident: If any Man ſhould deny it, let him look upon the <hi>Abdomen</hi> and extream Parts, and his Eyes are enough to convince him. Well then the Serum being thus ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (pray obſerve) and the Maſs of Blood not enough diluted: The oral Glands muſt neceſſarily be defrauded of their due Moiſture and conſequently Thirſt excited. But ſtill you harp up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame String: Thoſe Medicines which reſtore the Conſiſtence of the Blood, cannot well be ſuppoſed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair it. Now Acids reſtore it; and Steel in particular. <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Steel is of excellent Uſe, and a very great Reſtaurative is not to be deny'd. But under Favour, tho' you diſcourſe very ingeniouſly of the Nature of Steel: Yet all you have ſaid will not amount to a Proof of it's being an Acid. I am ſtill inclined to think it is an Alkaly. For
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151838:10"/>tho' it does not diſcover it ſelf to be ſuch by it's Colour, yet, it plainly does by it's Effects, <hi>viz.</hi> It's Fermentation with Acids. If, notwithſtanding this <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon,</hi> you will needs have it to be an Acid, why then one Acid will ferment with another; and ſo one Alkaly with another: wherefore, tho' we ſhould ſubſcribe to the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> that Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies are the Original of all Diſtempers, yet 'tis hard to exclude the Uſe of them in general in diſtempers. For ſome Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies or other might be found out that ſhould diſpute it with theſe offending Alkalies. You are pleaſed to quote <hi>Beeker</hi> for a Confirmation of the Acidity of Steel. The chief Sentence of the Citation ſeems to be this. <hi>Hoc tantum hic loci allegabo, omne acidum ſubſtantiae martialis eſſe, in quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> oleo, pinguedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, fuligine, limo, ſilice &amp; arenâ, imo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ipſâ flammâ reperibile, &amp; ad oculum demonſtrari poſſe; quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ergo naturae Acidae &amp; martialis ſunt, illa poteſtatem habent Alkali tanquam ſubſtantiam metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum mercurialem alterandi &amp; tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi.</hi> If I apprehend the Senſe of the Author, this does not make ſo much for you. But ſuppoſe it did, <hi>Beeker</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151838:10"/>was never reckon'd Infallible. And tho' <hi>Chalybs</hi> were an Acid, it does not follow, becauſe one Acid will renew the State of the Blood, that others will do ſo too. But ſince we have ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen on this Subject, <hi>viz.</hi> the Strengthning the Maſs of Blood; let us ſee what other Medicines beſides <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybs</hi> are ſubſervient to this End. And here I ſuppoſe your bitter Herbs may not be <hi>infimi ſubſellii.</hi> 'Tis needleſs to prove it; for hardly any <hi>Phyſitian</hi> but what has experienced it. I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you will dare to ſay, there is any Thing of an Acid in theſe, ſince you know very well that Alkaly may be extracted from moſt, if not all of them. So that poor Alkaly is effectual in ſome Caſes you ſee. But then (<hi>you ſay</hi>) <hi>Oak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark, Biſtort, Tormentile, Comfrey-roots</hi> and others of that Tribe will reduce the Blood to Conſiſtence. <hi>Anſw.</hi> That they are aſtringent I grant; whether they will reduce the Blood or invigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate it's depauperated Principles, I much queſtion. 'Tis very rare to ſee them preſcribed in <hi>Dropſies, Cackexies</hi> and the like Diſtempers where the Blood is poor and low. They are proper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151838:11"/>in Fluxes by virtue of their aſtringent Faculty. But then they owe this Aſtringency to Acids. Whether they do or not it matters not much. But why may not this Quality be derived as well from the Terreſtrious as the Salt Particles of theſe Vegetables: Since <hi>Bol. Arm. Terra Lemnia</hi> and other plain Earths are very Stiptick. I do not ſay, theſe Earths are ſo ſimple as to have no manner of Salt in them, but ſurely they have very little Acid. Another <hi>Object.</hi> was: If Alkalies did always offend and cauſe Pain, it muſt follow that Acids muſt give Eaſe: But I aſſure you, I have often experienced the contrary; for up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Exhibition of <hi>Rheniſh, White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine</hi> and other Acids, I have found the [<hi>Gouty</hi>] Pains immediately exaſperated, and many times it has been a long while e're they went off.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not repeat your whole Anſwer to this, but ſumm up the moſt material Parts of it. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not improbable, but upon giving a ſmall quantity of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid, where there is a large quantity of Alkaly lodg'd on any Part, ſo as to cauſe Pain, it may only in part diſſolve the Alkaly, which was before more fix'd,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151838:11"/>and ſo by accident exaſperate the Pain, whereas by continuing the Uſe of the Acid, the Alkaly would be perfectly diſſolved and extirpated, and ſo the Pain would altogether vaniſh. But Pain being ſometimes exaſperated more upon the firſt giving of them in too ſmall Quantities, has I doubt not, been one great. Cauſe of deterring People from proceeding in the Uſe of them, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of attributing to them the Cauſe of Pain. <hi>Reply,</hi> This I confeſs is a good ſound Solution, and would admit of no Reply, if it did but hang together with what follows. For here Acids cauſe Pain, becauſe they are not taken in Quantity ſufficient. By and by they produce the ſame Effect, becauſe they are taken in too great Quantity. For theſe are your own Words. And for the Pain you ſay, you have often found to be excited upon the giving <hi>Rheniſh</hi> and <hi>White-wine,</hi> I have aſſign'd a Reaſon for that, if they are drunk in too large Quantities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis plain then, that neither too little or too much Acid muſt be taken. Now I fancy it would be a difficult Matter for you or any Man elſe to determine the Quantity. 'Tis enough
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151838:12"/>to employ the Wits of a <hi>Virtuoſo.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if you remember what you have laid down in your <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> Acids cannot be taken in too great Quantity: For the Alkaline Gouty Particles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the Blood: Indeed, if all theſe Particles were ſubdued, then to load the Blood with Acids would be ſuperfluous. But this I fear you cannot ſay, you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver experienced. I ſhould be very glad to hear you could. It would be an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Phyſick to ſome purpoſe. Another <hi>Object.</hi> was. Again, if the <hi>Gout</hi> proceed from an Alkaly, what is the Reaſon you uſe ſo much <hi>Saſſafras</hi> in it's Cure? Is <hi>Saſſafras</hi> an Acid, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſubdue this Alkaly. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I can cure the <hi>Gout,</hi> if there were no ſuch thing as <hi>Saſſafras.</hi> I only uſe <hi>Saſſafras</hi> in <hi>Apozems</hi> as a proper Vehicle to dilute other Medicines in the Stomach. But however <hi>Saſſafras</hi> is no contemptible Medicine, and if you will but give your ſelf the Trouble of diſtilling a Pound in <hi>Retort per ſe,</hi> if you afterwards reckon <hi>Saſſafras</hi> amongſt the Number of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies, I am miſtaken; and if I am I ſhall willingly own it. <hi>Reply,</hi> That you ſhould uſe <hi>Saſſafras</hi> on purpoſe to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151838:12"/>diluto other Medicines, methinks is no fair way of arguing. I did never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill any <hi>Saſſafras</hi> in a <hi>Retort,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can pronounce nothing poſitively of it's Nature. But I am of Opinion, that by it's Effects it may much better be ranged under Alkalies than Acids. I fear 'twill be a hard task for you to prove it an Acid, which yet you ought to do to make your Practice <hi>conſonant</hi> to your <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> unleſs you will have recourſe to it as a Specific. <hi>Object.</hi> I have only a Word or two to ſpeak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the green Colour of Syrup of Violets, and ſo I have done. I believe it may be turned green without an Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. On the Exhibition of it to Infants it comes away green very often, and brings away a great deal of green Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by ſtool; and yet I believe they do not abound with Alkalies. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I own that upon the Exhibition of Syrup of Violets to Infants, it will frequently occaſion green ſtools: But from whence doth that proceed, but from it's Mixture with the Bile in the ſmall Guts? And that Bile is an Alkaly, I know not any one that doubts. <hi>Reply,</hi> Every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy knows that Bile is an Alkaly and of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151838:13"/>a greeniſh Colour: yet 'tis much to be queſtioned, whether it occaſions theſe green ſtools. For <hi>First,</hi> The Colour of it is altered in the <hi>Duodenum,</hi> by it's mixture with the <hi>Pancreatick</hi> Juyde. <hi>Secondly,</hi> If this were ſo, whence is it that in adult Perſons, even of the moſt Bilious Conſtitutions, we ſeldom or never find the Excrements green. The yellow Colour of the Excrements is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually imputed to Bile. <hi>Object.</hi> You may read in a late Author of undoubted Credit, that upon an Infant's ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Doſe of <hi>Teſtaceous</hi> Powder, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinaray Ferment was raiſed in the Stomach of the Child. Now how could this be done if it had not an Acid to work upon? Beſides does not Experience ſhew, that nothing is ſo proper in Infants Diſtempers as Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Acids may abound in the Stomach and cauſe a Diſorder, but in no other Parts of the Body. <hi>Reply,</hi> This Doctrin ſeems to me very precari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and if I can but ſhake it, a great Part of your <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> muſt be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>Firſt,</hi> then give me leave to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, how theſe Acids come to abound in the Stomack. Here you are pleaſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151838:13"/>to deny an innate Ferment: This Acid Liquor muſt by no means proceed from the Veſſels or Glands of the Ventricle: But is convey'd thither from the ſaliva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Glands. That <hi>Saliva</hi> is an Acid, and does deſcend to the Stomach is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evident. But why you ſhould take no Notice of it's proper Glands, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee. Nature does ſeldom bungle in her Operations, and diſpoſe things at random. Therefore ſince ſhe has pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſuch a parcel of excretory Veſſels in the Stomach, 'tis irrational to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they are of no Uſe. But to come to the Point. I hope to convince you preſently, that Acids exiſt in the Blood as well as the Stomach. And in order to this, I ſhall have no need to carry them from the Stomach to the Blood, as ſome have done; but ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prove them preexiſtent in the Blood, even by the Rules of your own <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> We have an old Maxim in Philoſophy; <hi>Nihil dat quod in ſe non habet.</hi> How this Acid current of <hi>Saliva,</hi> therefore ſhould ſpring from a Fountain void of all Acidity (for the <hi>Serum</hi> muſt be it's Fountain) I cannot ſo eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. If any thing was capable of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151838:14"/>metamorphoſing this Alkaline <hi>Serum</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Acid, it muſt be the Texture of the Parts, thro' which it paſles. But this the Texture cannot do. For the Oral Glands have nothing of an Acid Ferment in them, or any alterative Faculty. They only ſeparate ſuch Particles as are adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their Pores. 'Tis true theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles before their Separation are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and intermix'd with the other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that you cannot make any ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſcovery of them; yet 'tis no good Logic to conclude, that they are not in the Blood. 'Tis very ſeldom that we can perceive any thing of Bile in it when drawn either by Colour or Taſte, yet ſurely 'tis never without Bile. And the Liver does not generate <hi>Choler</hi> (as ſome ignorantly ſuppoſe) it only ſtrains it off from the Blood. For if it's Glands are any way impaired either by <hi>Schirrus, Exulceration, &amp;c.</hi> the Blood is ſo far from wanting <hi>Choler,</hi> that it immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately abounds with it; wherefore ſince Bile is really preexiſtent in the Blood till to it's Separation, 'tis very rational to ſuppoſe that Spittle is ſo too: For they are both percolated after the ſame Manner, tho' not thro' the ſame Glands.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151838:14"/>And indeed I admire that your repeated <hi>Analyſes</hi> of the Blood ſhould produce nothing of an Acid. I had almoſt ſaid, you overlook it: If we may believe Mr. <hi>Boyl,</hi> the Blood is not without Acids. And give me leave to tell you, that you do not deal fairly with Alkalies; you derogate from the Dignity of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when you make them wholy excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious. Is there a more noble Juyce in human Bodies than Bile, than Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizated Bile? Sure I am, no true Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction can be performed without it. A thouſand other good Offices might be attributed to it. This is all <hi>Sir,</hi> I have to offer in maintenance of my Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If I have expreſt my ſelf indecent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any where, do not impute it to Rudeneſs or Diſreſpect. Your good Nature cannot but eaſily find out the true Occaſion of it. God forbid I ſhould treat you as a Gentleman has lately done. I think we are all of us obliged to you for your Care and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry. Whether Acids are of univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Uſe, will be determined in time. I believe they will never prove ſo. But certainly they are of ſome Uſe: And in this you have gained a conſiderable
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151838:15"/>Point, and done the World very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Service. For many of our old Galenical Brethren had a great Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to them: Nay the moſt moderate Uſe of that mild Acid, Vinegar has been declaimed againſt for ſouring the Blood: And for other Acids of a ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Nature, they have repreſented them to their Patients as hurtful as the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom of a Mad-dog. Your Enemies cannot but acknowledg the Generoſity of your Temper in your not being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged at the Snarls of ſuch <hi>Cynicks:</hi> Nor even at the baſe and villainous Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of ſome <hi>Chyrurgeons;</hi> who have meditated againſt your Life, becauſe you have put them in a fair Way to ſave that of others. I ſhould here conclude, and make no farther Obſervations on your <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> but that you deſire me and every one elſe, before we take up with any Thing that comes from you, to examin it in the Balances of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Experience. Pardon me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if I adventure to examin ſome Paſſages in your <hi>Eſſay</hi> of <hi>Alkaly</hi> and <hi>Acid.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151838:15"/>
            <head>OF THE <hi>Small-Pox.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE firſt Thing that occurs there is the <hi>Small-Pox.</hi> You ſuppoſe it (in <hi>pages</hi> 3 and 13) to proceed from an <hi>Intromiſſion</hi> of <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> Particles, or Particles of a different Nature and Texture from the Blood, into it: By means of which Particles the Blood is put into a very great hurry and diſorder, in order to throw off it's Enemy: And that the Place that Nature deſigns the Diſcharge of theſe Particles by, is the Cutaneous Glands. Now the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences that you obſerv'd to attend the Uſe of Alkalies, where the throwing out of more Puſtles than Nature deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the deſtroying the Globules of the Blood, and a waſte of too great Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of <hi>Serum.</hi> This <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> how
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151838:16"/>ingeniouſly ſoever contrived, I fear will look ſomewhat ſtrange by and by, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when compared with your Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. Well then, the Occaſion of the <hi>Small-Pox</hi> is an <hi>Intromiſſion</hi> of <hi>Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> Particles. Here you term the <hi>morbifick</hi> Particles <hi>Heterogeneous,</hi> but do not much care to fix the Nature of them, I ſuppoſe they muſt be of an Alkaline if any. For nothing but Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaly with you is the Principal of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Now I ſhall endeavour to prove that theſe <hi>intromitted</hi> Particles cannot well be of an Alkaline Nature: And tho' they were ſo, that a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Uſe of them could not be always Prejudicial, but ſometimes of great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. <hi>Firſt</hi> then, theſe Particles cannot be Alkaline, becauſe no tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Account can be given from the Rules of your <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> how theſe Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies ſhould excite ſuch a diſorderly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Blood. The Globules you ſay are broken, but you explain not the Manner of their being broken. They muſt either be broken by Accenſion (the vital Flame burning very furiouſly) or by Fermentation? 'Twill be very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to find out another Way. Now
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151838:16"/>Alkalies cannot well accend the Blood; Acid and Sulphur (with you) being the only <hi>Pabulum</hi> of Flame. Aſhes or Alkalies ſhould rather choak it. But here I only argue againſt your <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis</hi> of <hi>Accenſion.</hi> I do not deny but Alkalies may raiſe ſome ſlight diſorders in the Blood. They may occaſion ſome Fevours. But they are never ſo ill na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured as to break the Globules. Acids are much better armed to do this Work. Neither <hi>Secondly,</hi> Can they be ſo eaſily found guilty of Fermentation; ſince you exclude all Acids from the Blood. Theſe Salts do not uſe to be ſo nimble, they are dull enough of themſelves, unleſs an Acid Antagoniſt rouſes their Courage. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> grant theſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tromitted</hi> Particles were Alkaline (which you have not proved hitherto) yet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies could not be always improper in this Diſtemper. Indeed when the Blood runs. High, and it's Motion is very violent, then to add Alkaly, to the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tromitted</hi> Alkaly would be highly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious. But if this Motion is natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weak, or is accidentally check'd, ſo as to be unable to promote an Excreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151838:17"/>of the Particles, what harm is it to help it on with Alkalies? There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more uſual than upon taking Cold, or by too liberal an Uſe of cooling Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, for the <hi>Pox,</hi> as ſoon as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to ſtrike in again (as they call it) or vaniſh: And if they do not ſtrike in, they maturate very ſlowly, the Patient being fevoriſh all the while. In ſuch a caſe as this, you may give Acids <hi>ad infinitum</hi> to no purpoſe, or allow your Patients as much ſmall-Beer as you pleaſe; it ſhall not fill up the <hi>Puſtules;</hi> 'twill be a hard Matter for Dame Nature to eſcape a drowning. And I appeal to your Learned Society, if upon ſuch Accidents as theſe, <hi>pulv. e chel. marg. pp.</hi> and above all <hi>ead. Serpentar. Virgin.</hi> are not of wonderful Uſe. Indeed in a <hi>Confluent-Pox,</hi> you may bleed, indulge ſmall-Beer liberally, give Acids; and all will not ſtop, they will but regulate the Motion of the Blood: But if you ſhould obſerve the ſame Method in more gentle <hi>Poxes,</hi> 'tis much but the Patient pays dear for it; and therefore you act like an honeſt good <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> being more tender of others Lives than your
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151838:17"/>own <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> in preſcribing nothing of Acids in <hi>Variolis Benignis.</hi> Neither is it good (I confeſs) to tamper too much with Alkalies here. But this I aſſure you (having often engaged with this Diſtemper) that I never ſaw the <hi>Teſtaceous</hi> Powders moderately ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred produce any ill Effect even in the moſt favourable <hi>Poxs:</hi> Which is more (I verily believe) than can be ſaid of Acids. And here I cannot but take notice of one Thing, which I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in it's proper Place. Alkalies you acknowledg are good Medicines for Children, becauſe they are of a mild Nature. Are there not Acids of a mild Nature as well as Alkalies? Why then do you not exhibit thoſe mild Acids? Indeed you preſcribe them in ſome particular Caſes not without Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. But they will hardly ever be found ſo generally effectual as Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. But to return to the <hi>Small-Pox:</hi> You diſpleaſe me in giving <hi>Syrup. de Meconio.</hi> even upon their firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion. Methinks, it ſhould hinder their Eruption. The worthy <hi>Syden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that true Patron of a cold <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151838:18"/>ſeemed to be ſenſible of this, and therefore never preſcribed it till they were all come out. One Word more and I have done with this. If the <hi>Pox</hi> were occaſioned by the <hi>Intromiſſion</hi> of <hi>Heterogeneous</hi> Particles, a Man might as well labour under them ten times as once. But this is contrary to Experience, I never ſaw any Man that had the true <hi>Pox</hi> twice.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151838:18"/>
            <head>OF THE <hi>Scurvy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THAT the <hi>Testaceous</hi> Powders are of no great Uſe in the <hi>Scurvy:</hi> That there is ſomething of a <hi>Lixivious</hi> fix'd Alkaly in <hi>Scrobutical</hi> Blood: That <hi>Tartar</hi> and it's Preparations are proper to correct this Salt, I verily believe. And yet notwithſtanding all this, there are a Sort of Alkalies in the World that may be ſeaſonably apply'd even in this very Diſtemper. 'Tis well known that the Stomach as well as Blood of <hi>Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> Perſons is often out of order. They complain of a bad Appetite and worſe Digeſtion. Now tho' <hi>Tartarous</hi> Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines may do ſomething toward the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of the ill Symptoms of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach as well as thoſe of the Blood: Yet they do not operate ſo powerfully
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151838:19"/>as your digeſtive bitter Herbs, whoſe Salts are undeniably Alkaline.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if you give the Bitters by themſelves to ſome <hi>Scorbutical</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, they will warm their Blood a little too much. And it may not be amiſs to preſcribe Acids with them. For ſince, neither will work a Cure ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, the beſt way I think is to unite their Forces. Not but that Acids by themſelves (I grant you) will do the buſineſs, where the <hi>Ventricle</hi> is under no Indiſpoſition. But by the way you do not ſeem to have anſwer'd a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Objection, which has been ſtarted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your <hi>Doctrin</hi> of the <hi>Scurvy</hi> in your <hi>Appendix. Objection,</hi> You ſay, that the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is occaſioned by too great a Quantity of <hi>Alkalious</hi> Particles in the Blood, and is only cured by Acids. If ſo, how comes it to paſs, that thoſe People who live upon nothing almoſt, but highly-ſeaſoned Meat, are more troubled with the <hi>Scurvy</hi> than other People, when you own Salt to be an Acid? <hi>Anſwer,</hi> This does not proceed from their eating a larger Quantity of Salt than other People, but from their eating more Fleſh and Fiſh than other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151838:19"/>which abound with <hi>Alkalious</hi> Particles, and the Moiſtneſs of the Air. <hi>Reply,</hi> Whether a moiſt Air breeds the <hi>Scurvy</hi> is much to be queſtioned; but that a ſalt Air will is very plain, 'Tis obſervable, that thoſe People which live in the moſt Fenny Places of our Inland-Counties, are not ſo miſerably Plagu'd with this Diſtemper, as others which dwell in Hilly Places, if by the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. There is hardly a more dry Mountainous Country in <hi>England</hi> than the <hi>North-part</hi> of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and at the ſame time no Place more miſerably over-run with the <hi>Scurvy.</hi> What Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can be given for this, but the Saltneſs of the Air? And I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that the meaner Sort of the ſame County, whoſe Diet is chiefly on <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> Beef and <hi>Newfoundland</hi> Fiſh, are much more obnoxious to this Diſeaſe than others, who eat greater Quantities of unſeaſoned Fleſh and Fiſh.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151838:20"/>
            <head>OF <hi>Rheumatiſms.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS for <hi>Rheumatiſms,</hi> tho' ſomething might be objected to your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Serum's Viſcoſity</hi> in that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, yet I ſhall wave it. We will not quarrel about the <hi>Theory,</hi> when we agree well enough in the <hi>Practick.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:151838:20"/>
            <head>OF <hi>Conſumptions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>COME we laſt of all to <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> And here you make Acids very beneficial. This Aſſertion of yours, tho' it ſtrikes an Eight to your <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis,</hi> will hardly do ſo to Experience: 'tis flatly repugnant to it. You cannot be inſenſible that a <hi>Catarrh</hi> is the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Harbinger to this fatal Diſtemper: That in all <hi>Catarrhs</hi> the Blood is in a Fuſion; as is evident from the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Excretion or Diſtillation of <hi>Rheum</hi> from the Glands of the <hi>Pharynx</hi> upon the Lungs, and it's throwing out great Plenty of clear Spittle (<hi>alias</hi> clear Acid) from the <hi>Salivatory-ducts:</hi> And you know well enough that Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Lime-Juyce, Stale-Beer, Sowr-Wines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſo far from allaying
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151838:21"/>this <hi>Fluxion,</hi> that they incontinently promote it. Be pleaſed then but to meditate on theſe Premiſes, and the Concluſion will be obvious enough. You talk indeed of Oyl of <hi>Sulphur,</hi> that it has wrought great Cures in a <hi>Phthiſis:</hi> But did you ever ſee theſe Cures? You are not pleaſed to give one Inſtance of this kind: Tho' you furniſh us with ſeveral on other Diſtempers, to confirm your <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis.</hi> You quote <hi>Helmont</hi> for a Story of an old Souldier, that was ſtrangly preſerved by Oyl of <hi>Sulphur.</hi> But the Man was not at all <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> as I can find. It muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in <hi>Aſthmatical</hi> Caſes, where the Phlegm is very thick and viſcous; and the <hi>Serum</hi> it ſelf glutinous; that Oyl of <hi>Sulphur</hi> may be of excellent Uſe by reaſon of it's inciding or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating Faculty. But in a <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> properly ſo called, it ſeems to be deſtructive to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. I ſhould now make an End; but that I meet with ſomething in the <hi>Appendix,</hi> that I cannot well paſs by. 'Tis honeſt Mr. <hi>Kemp's</hi> Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um on Vinegar. That a moderate
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151838:21"/>Uſe of Vinegar may be agreable to ſome Conſtitutions no body can deny; tho' I fear an immoderate to none at all. That <hi>Acetum,</hi> eſpecially when mix'd with <hi>Alexipharmacks,</hi> is a noble Medicine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in peſtilential Diſtempers is more than probable. But I am ſure 'tis far from being a <hi>Panacaea.</hi> Let a lean Man eat Vinegar till dooms-day, he ſhall not improve his Habit of Body, or grow fat upon it; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you aſſert Fat to be generated of Acid Particles. I ſhall not anatomize your Notion of Fat at preſent, or the Manner of it's being made. Suffice it to obſerve to you that I never heard of this pinguefying Virtue of Acids till now. I could give you many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to the contrary; but I believe no body will be angry with me, if I ſpare my Pains. However I ſhall ſingle out one to ſatisfy you, that Acids are hurtful in <hi>Catarrhs,</hi> and are too apt to make Men lean. A certain Gentleman, whoſe Name you know (but I muſt not mention it) was highly ſeaſoned about 14 Months time with the <hi>Scurvy.</hi> He had a great Fancy, that <hi>Sevil</hi>-Oranges and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151838:22"/>Lemons would rebuke this Malady: Accordingly furniſhes himſelf on the firſt opportunity with a large Parcel of them. His Medicines proving ſo pleaſant, he doſed himſelf very liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them, and eat ſeveral of them in a day. Obſerve the Event, he had not continued this Courſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Fortnight, before he fell into a moſt violent <hi>Catarrh.</hi> He ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſenſible of his Error, threw away the Reſidue of his Fruit, and timely applyed himſelf to aſtringent and agglutinating Medicins, ſome Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies being intermix'd. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the daily Uſe of theſe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Preſcriptions, he grew very thin, his Cough trouble him much; and 'twas a conſiderable while e're he recovered the Fault. This is all I have to offer againſt you: I believe we might be reconciled if you would but let fall your <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> a little, and not ſtrain it quite ſo high. Acids no doubt are of Uſe, and ſo are Alkalies too. Wherefore, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult our own, or our Patients Safety, <hi>medio eamus.</hi> I have only one Thing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151838:22"/>to beg of You and the Reader, That you would Pardon what you ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs in theſe Papers. Which I hope you will do the ſooner, upon Promiſe of my arreſting my Pen, and never troubling the World again with the impertinent Notions, <hi>of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant FRANCIS TUTHILL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
